Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, good ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*, the only
non today's the only non שבת *Shabbos* or יום טוב Yom Tov
*Yom Tov* day of the year that we don't say מזמור לתודה
*Mizmor Lesoda* just so you know.
Okay.
They do by the way.
They do? Really? Wow. Okay anyway, today we do we're on דף
עט *Daf Ayin Tes*, we pick up about 10 lines down, two
dots, מכר חצר ומכר זבלה *Machar hachatzer umachar zivlah*. If you sell
a dung heap or a whatever, a place for a garbage space,
so you're actually selling the dirt, you know, the ground or the
hole in the ground, but you also sell the manure that and
the garbage that's there, which actually has a value particularly if it's
manure. Okay and then it says if you sell a well a
cistern you sell the water in it and so on. תנן התם
*Tnan Hasam*, we taught over there in מעילה meilah *Me'ila*. כל הראוי
למזבח lemizbeiach, ולא לבדק הבית l'bedek habayis, *Kol harauy lamizbe'ach velo lebedek
habayis*, anything that is fit to be put on the מזבח mizbeiach.
*mizbe'ach* but not fit for בדק הבית bedek habais *bedek habayis* for
construction purposes of the בית המקדש bais hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. And
that something fit for the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbe'ach* would obviously be like
a קרבן korban *korban*, an animal without a blemish. And it's not
fit for construction purposes because first of all you don't build a
sheep right into the walls of the בית המקדש bais hamikdash, *Beis
Hamikdash*, but it's also not fit because you're not supposed to use
an unblemished animal for to sanctify it for another purpose like if
you want to sanctify this sheep that it should be sold and
the proceeds should go to the בית המקדש bais hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*
you actually transgress a positive command because
an unblemished animal if you're going to sanctify it should only be
sanctified for actually the מזבח mizbeiach. *mizbe'ach* itself. Now what's important to
sort of say at the outset here is that there are two
different sets of terms which are often conflate identified but they're not.
Meaning
one set of terms
is קדושת הגוף Kedushas HaGuf. *Kedushat Haguf*
and קדושת דמים kedushas damim, *Kedushat Damim*. Now what that means קדושת
הגוף Kedushas HaGuf. *Kedushat Haguf* means the thing itself is going to
be used, thing itself will be used in some sort of בית
המקדש bais hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* purpose, קדושת דמים kedushas damim. *Kedushat Damim*
means the value, meaning you're going to sell it and use the
proceeds. Sell and use the proceeds. Okay.
Like a timberline doesn't mean your. Right.
Now there's another set of terms, that's one. There's another set of
terms which is קדושת kedushat מזבח mizbeiach,
*Kedushat Mizbe'ach* and קדושת בדק הבית Kedushas Bedek HaBayis *Kedushat Bedek Habayis*.
קדושת מזבח mizbeiach *Kedushat Mizbe'ach* means it's going to go on the
מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*, so those are sacrifices, although it could also be,
I don't know, flour, wine, something that's going to go on the
מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. קדושת בדק הבית Kedushas Bedek HaBayis *Kedushat Bedek Habayis*
could be, I don't know, like a, now here it divides into
two because there's a normal assumption, oh, so קדושת מזבח *Kedushat Mizbe'ach*
is קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf. *Kedushat Haguf* because it's going on the
מזבח *mizbe'ach*, that's true. Okay, קדושת בדק הבית Kedushas Bedek HaBayis *Kedushat
Bedek Habayis* is going to go for use for upkeep and maintenance
or whatever, that's קדושת דמים kedushas damim. *Kedushat Damim*, that's you're going
to sell it and use the money, not necessarily. There's two types
of קדושת בדק הבית Kedushat Bedek ha-Bayit *Kedushat Bedek Habayis*. There's a
קדושת בדק הבית bedek habais *Kedushat Bedek Habayis* which is which is
going to be using the thing itself, like you could do like
some two by fours, like some beams, you know, or whatever, or
gold or stuff that you're going to use.
Or a plow for the
field of הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*. Ah, that would not be קדושת הגוף
*Kedushat Haguf*, קדושת הגוף *Kedushat Haguf* means that הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* is
using it but they're not using it directly to like in a
קדושה kedushah *kedusha* capacity. Okay, like קדושת דמים kedushas damim. *Kedushat Damim*
doesn't have to mean you use the proceeds, that's true. I mean,
but you're interested in it because of the income it'll produce. קדושת
דמים Kedushas Damim. *Kedushat Damim* I always say this, it's like what
they say the cynic knows the cost of everything and the value
of nothing. So קדושת דמים Kedushas Damim *Kedushat Damim* is only interested
interesting because of its value. All right.
What would you do with the שור *shor* that I, you
know, donate to plow the field of הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*? That's קדושת
דמים Kedushat damim, *Kedushat Damim*. You're interested in it because of the
income it'll produce, not because you're going to use the thing itself.
Okay. So this is stuff that goes into the actual temple itself,
these these would sort of be like construction materials, okay, so that
could be, you know, materials.
Or marble for the floor directly.
Right. So those would be the קדושת הגוף *Kedushat Haguf*, but it
could also be קדושת דמים *Kedushat Damim* is pretty much everything else
that you're interested in because of because of its value or because
of the money that it produces. All right, anyway, so those are
the different terms. So we're saying anything that is fit למזבח lemizbeiach.
*lamizbe'ach* that's in this category, okay,
ולא לבדק הבית lebedek habayit. *velo lebedek habayis* or the opposite, it's
fit for for building into the wall it's like a beam or
some gold but it's not fit for bringing to the. as a
sacrifice on the altar. לא למזבח lemizbeiach ולא לבדק הבית. lebedek habayit,
Now neither of those, that would be the קדושת דמים, okay, that
would be the stuff that is going to be used for the
proceeds and it's not something that's going to be put on the
altar, not something that's going to be built into the temple,
but it's valuable for its actual value. In any one of those
three cases,
מועלין בהן ובמה שבתוכן. moalin bahen ube mah shebesochan. There is מעילה
meilah that applies to them and to anything that they might contain.
What's the example? כיצד, keitzad, how's this possible?
הקדיש בור מלא מים. hektish bor malei mayim. You sanctified a well
filled with water. Now the water actually is not fit for the
מזבח. You might think why not? How about ניסוך המים? nisuch hamayim?
How about water used for מנחות? menachos? But there, simple type of
rainwater collected in a well is not considered to be fit for
the altar. Okay, so that's an example of...
Rainwater would have to be a spring?
What? It would have to be a spring. Okay, so even so,
but it would be used, the רשב"ם rashbam says, it is usable
for בדק הבית bedek habais, because you can use it to make
cement. You can use it to mix...
Why is it neither then?
No, we're going to have every something that falls into every one
of the categories. So that's for the רשב"ם rashbam is something that
is fit for בדק הבית bedek habais, actually, surprisingly. בור מלא מים...
bor malei mayim... אשפות מלאות זבל. ashpos mleio hazevel. I'm
not up to that yet. Okay, כיצד, keitzad, הקדיש
בור מלא מים, hektish bor malei mayim, אשפות מלאות זבל. ashpos mleio
hazevel. Okay,
so that, as you might want to guess, dung heaps or whatever,
are not fit for the altar or for בדק הבית, bedek habais.
that's just for their value.
Is there no עניין inyan of it is really just not nice
to do for what?
What do you mean?
Appropriate? זבל? zevel?
If you could use dung in making cement, you would, I suppose,
but we're assuming that's not the case. שובך מלא יונים, shovach malei
yonim, or a pigeon coop filled with pigeons, and with pigeons actually
can be used למזבח, l'mizbeach. so there's something that can be used
למזבח. lamizbeach. ושדה מלא עשבים, vesadeh malei asavim, that's also something that
can be used not למזבח or for בדק הבית, bedek habais, okay,
what are you going to do with grass?
ואילן עושה פירות, veilan osei peiros, a tree that has fruit on
it. So there actually that's not מזבח or בדק הבית. bedek habais.
Now you might say wait a minute, what about ביכורים? bikurim? But
ביכורים bikurim is like תרומה, terumah, it goes to the כהן. kohen.
You do a ritual in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but it's
not offered to the on the מזבח. So those things in the
end, in particular, the tree itself is probably fit for בדק הבית,
bedek habayis. but anyway, the fruit is only קדושת דמים. In all
those cases, מועלין בהן ובמה שבתוכן. moalin bahen ube mah shebesochan. It
doesn't matter which category they fall into, whether they can be used
for one purpose or another, for the מזבח, to directly be built
into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, to sell and use their proceeds,
מעילה meilah applies to all of them. Now, the one interesting thing,
well it's going to get interesting in a minute from another perspective,
but the immediate interesting thing that the ראשונים rishonim stop on here
is the case about the שדה sadeh and the בור bor because
there's a general principle that there's not מעילה meilah by קרקע. karka.
So רשב"ם rashbam here thinks that there is מעילה meilah by קרקע
karka and everybody goes a little crazy. And but the question is
what would be an example where there would be actual מעילה meilah
with the בור bor itself? So one example תוספות tosafos gives is
that well maybe you uprooted a piece of a clump of earth
from the well and from the cistern and you got הנאה hana'ah
from that. Of course, at that point you're not being נהנה neheneh
then directly from the well, you're being נהנה neheneh once it's no
longer a well, once it's pulled out of the ground. But the
רמב"ן ramban has a more interesting answer. The רמב"ן ramban says, and
it's also interesting because it ties into a גמרא gemara we learned
before. The רמב"ן ramban says let's say you built a wall within
the well, like you built a brick wall within the well on
the inside wall. So that would be תלוש ולבסוף חיברו, talush ulebasof
chibro, so if you then got הנאה hana'ah which according to a
whole earlier debate is a question whether it's considered קרקע karka or
not קרקע. karka. So assuming it's not קרקע, karka, that would be
a way in which you got benefit from the well or from
the cistern, but it was actually not considered קרקע karka because you
were getting benefit from the wall. You leaned against the wall, you
cooled yourself off down there, you scratched your back against it, so
you got some benefit from it, but it technically wasn't מחובר לקרקע.
mechubar lekarka. But anyway, that's one interesting discussion. It's interesting that they
stop to discuss it about the cistern, it also mentioned שדה מלא
עשבים, sadeh malei asavim, okay, which is a field. But anyway, it
is worth noting that there's a whole question because this seems to
ignore the question about קרקע karka and מחובר לקרקע mechubar lekarka where
there's a general assumption that there is not מעילה meilah by those.
I think I missed something more basic. Here there's a ברייתא braisa
says if it's not if it's ראוי rauy neither to the מזבח
nor to בדק הבית. bedek habayis.
That's one category, there were three.
So why would there be מעילה me'ilah for something that's not שייך
shayach to anything?
Because it's proceeds. I sanctify my car to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, is going to sell it
and use that money, but the car itself cannot be put on
the altar, cannot be built in the wall. That's קדושת דמים. That's
קדושת דמים.
ולא ראוי לא למזבח ולא לבדק הבית V'lo ra-uy lo l'mizbeach v'lo
l'bedek habayis is a way of saying קדושת דמים.
Yes, it's only valuable for its, I mean, it gets a little
complicated because there could also be like קדושת דמים למזבח. Kedushas Damim
l'mizbeach. If I sanctify let's say something with a מום, mum, so
you can't use the thing itself, it doesn't have קדושת הגוף. You're
going to sell it and use the, you're going to be פודה
podeh it and use the proceeds, but the proceeds are then going
to go to the מזבח, right?
But קדושת בדק הבית is a, something to have קדושת בדק הבית
and not itself be ראוי לבדק הבית ra-uy l'bedek habayis because I
sanctify my car, it has קדושת בדק הבית because that's ultimately where
its money is going to go, its value is going to go,
but it doesn't itself, it's not itself ראוי לבדק הבית ra-uy l'bedek
habayis because it's not going to be built straight into the בדק
הבית. So this is, so maybe this is a confusing, I'll take
off these arrows. Okay, this is the thing itself or the value,
and this is what purpose is it going to go to, okay?
So something, a קרבן korban has קדושת הגוף. You could have a,
you could have a strange case of let's say a קרבן korban
with, well not so strange, a קרבן korban, with a מום, mum,
which is sort of, you know, I mean there's some scenarios but
whatever, but where it's basically like a קדושת דמים למזבח. Kedushas Damim
l'mizbeach. All right? Because you're going to redeem it, but then the
money is going to go למזבח. Okay? So קדושת דמים is the
thing itself is going to be sold and the money is going
to go to some purpose, either this, you know, so this is
the purpose, the מזבח or בדק הבית.
Could you not take your car and take the proceeds to buy
שלמי ציבור, Shalmei Tzibur, right? Could you not do that?
No, that you can't do. What, if you're מקדיש makdish something that's
not ראוי למזבח ra-uy l'mizbeach that, that only has a קדושת דמים
לבדק הבית, Kedushas Damim l'Bedek HaBayis, you can't sort of switch it.
But anyway, but for something itself, the proceeds will be going לבדק
הבית, but the thing itself is not ראוי לבדק הבית. ra-uy l'bedek
habayis. Yes.
So regarding that last point you mentioned, so according to everyone else
with the רשב''ם, Rashbam, so if I מקדיש makdish my field but
then I decide I want to get a lawn of soft grass,
I'm not...
You're not allowed to. You're transgressing, but מעילה me'ilah. in the sense
of the sense of the consequence. Yeah, that's an important point to
point out. When we say יש בו מעילה yesh bo me'ilah or
אין בו מעילה, ein bo me'ilah, it's not the question just about
like do you transgress the prohibition about benefiting from הקדש, hekdesh it's
like do you add a fifth, do you bring a קרבן, korban
all of the laws of
מעילה.
me'ilah Am I allowed to, just so I understand this, a קרבן
korban, that has a מום mum now but I'm taking it to
the vet, it's going to get better, then you know, can I
מקדיש makdish it now to be?
Yeah, that's a מום עובר. mum over. Right. So, right, right to
that. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I mean, I have to remind myself whether
there's that איסור issur to be מקדיש makdish it when it has
a מום עובר. mum over. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. דבר Davar
now, that's okay, where were we? So now, that's the stage one.
That's fascinating but not yet directly relevant to our discussion. This is
all going to be related because our משנה Mishna discusses a well
filled with water. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אבל
הקדיש
בור ואחר כך נתמלא מים. Aval hikdish bor v'acharchach nitmalei mayim.
You sanctified a cistern and then it rained and it filled with
water. אף באחר כך נתמלא זבל, Af b'acharchach nitmalei zevel, or a
dunghill and then it was empty, it was just an empty plot
of land and then the animals went in and they did their
business there and then it became filled with manure. שובך ואחר כך
נתמלא יונים, Shovach v'acharchach nitmalei yonim,
or it was a pigeon coop and then the pigeons came and
flocked to it and filled it up. אילן ואחר כך נשא פירות,
Ilan v'acharchach
nasa
peiros,
you sanctified a tree and then it, and then it bore fruit.
שדה ואחר כך נתמלא עשבים, Sadeh v'acharchach nitmalei asabim, or field and
then it became filled with grass. מועלין בהן ואין מועלין במה שבתוכן
דברי רבי יהודה. Me'ilin bahen v'ein me'ilin b'mah shebeisochan divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
The מעילה me'ilah applies to the thing itself, so again there you,
it seems like there's מעילה me'ilah by the grass, by the field,
by the cistern, so we discussed that, but the thing that afterwards
came into it, you didn't sanctify that, so there is no מעילה
me'ilah by the water and by the pigeons and so on. רבי
יוסי אומר המקדיש השדה והאילן מועלין בהן ובגידוליהן מפני שהן גידולי הקדש.
Rabbi Yossi omer hamakdish hasadeh v'ha'ilan me'ilin bahen u'v'giduleihen mipnei shehen gidulei
hekdesh.
No, if you sanctify the field or the tree, and then presumably
the field gets grass and the tree gets fruit, then there is
מעילה me'ilah. by the thing that grew because those are things that
grew from הקדש. hekdesh So it seems like he's saying I'm not
disagreeing about the well that filled with water or the pigeon coops
that fill with pigeons or the, or the, you know, the grass,
the, whatever, the plot of land that gets dung, because that stuff
that's not, that doesn't, isn't produced by the thing you sanctified. But
if you sanctify a tree and it bears fruit and it's produced
by it, then that is, there is מעילה. me'ilah Now, these are
two, now, the question is, what is the reason there's no מעילה
meilah. in the, in the first category? In the category of let's
say the well that fills with water? Because the question all the
ראשונים Rishonim ask is they say I don't understand, if I own
a well and it rains and it fills with water, I own
the well. on the water. That's called a קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer,
right? If I own a, you know, a plot of land and
then the animals do their business there and that's dung and it's
הפקר hefker or whatever, then I own it because that's a קנין
חצר. kinyan chatzer. If I own a pigeon coop and, you know,
wild pigeons come and nest in it, I own it. That's a
קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So why doesn't הקדש hekdesh own it? And
if הקדש hekdesh owns this, then there should be מעילה. meilah. So
this is the question that everybody asks. So there are two interesting
answers. And this is very interesting, I find it at least,
but I'm a little bit of a nerd,
but I find it interesting. Okay? One answer is the רשב"ם Rashbam
and תוספות, Tosafot,
that הקדש hekdesh, doesn't have a קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer, which is
a little ironic, you know, because it's like כי לי הארץ, Ki
li ha'aretz, you know, everything is God's, right? כי גרים ותושבים אתם
עמדי, Ki gerim vetoshavim atem imadi, כל הנהנה מן העולם הזה בלא
ברכה כאילו מעל, Kol haneheneh min ha'olam hazeh belo brachah ke'ilu ma'al,
you know, anyway, everything belongs to God, but God doesn't have a
קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So the הקדש hekdesh. doesn't have a, not
God, הקדש hekdesh. doesn't have a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So it's
only a חידוש chiddush by a הדיוט, hedyot, a layperson. And even
if something הפקר hefker rose into the field of הקדש, hekdesh it
doesn't belong to הקדש. hekdesh That's the answer that תוספות Tosafot and
the רשב"ם Rashbam said, that there's no פסוק pasuk to ever tell
you there's a קנין חצר kinyan chatzer by הקדש. hekdesh And that's
why. Okay, why does it make sense?
Because
הקדש hekdesh requires כוונה. kavanah. It requires an active...
ah, so what you're saying is actually you're intuiting a different answer.
Because what the תוספות Tosafot and the רשב"ם Rashbam are saying is
הקדש hekdesh. doesn't even own the water that fell into the well.
Now comes along the רמב"ן Ramban and he says different. He says
no, one minute. We've got, I'm elaborating a little, but this is
basically what the רמב"ן Ramban says. We've got to distinguish
between הקדש hekdesh as a...
as like an entity that owns things,
right? So there's like, you know, like in Rome, right? I mean
the Vatican is extremely wealthy, there's a Vatican bank, they've got a
bank account, they own tons of stuff. Like so הקדש hekdesh as
a type of a corporation or you know an institution that has
ownership. That's one question. And then you have another question which is
the sanctity of the object. And what they say is they say
for an object to be sanctified
you need קדושת פה. kedushat peh. You need a verbal act to
sanctify it. I am מקדיש makdish my car לבדק הבית. That makes
the car holy. But let's say it rains and the rain falls
into a well of הקדש. hekdesh הקדש hekdesh owns that water. It's
theirs. They can sell it, they can use it. You don't have
a right to come take it. It fell into their field. It's
הפקר, hefker, they own it. But it's not קדוש. kadosh. It doesn't
have sanctity because it has not been sanctified. So if you use
it you don't transgress מעילה. meilah, So I really... it's a brilliant
distinction because it forces us to recognize that הקדש hekdesh here is
like playing two roles. That all of this is sort of like
is the object holy. Okay, but if I sanctify my car
לבדק הבית, בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. doesn't just care if the object
is holy, they care that they own the car and they can
now sell it and use the money. So הקדש hekdesh is two
things. הקדש hekdesh is like a status of an object that results
from it being assigned to God or to the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash and it is the ownership of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash.
of this object. Now sometimes you actually have that an object has
קדושה kedushah. but it's not owned by the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash
like a קרבן, korban, like or especially if you think about like
a קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. Right? According to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili, קדשים קלים ממון בעלים. Kodashim kalim mammon ba'alim. I take
this sheep and I say I'm sanctifying it as a שלמים. shlamim.
He says okay, it still belongs to you. It's your sheep that's
holy, that you have to bring as a קרבן, but it doesn't
belong to the בית המקדש. You're even going to... קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, excellent example! You're going to eat from it! Mostly you're going
to eat from it anyway, so it's yours with קדושה. kedushah So
there's a difference between the קדושה kedushah. of the object and the
ownership of the object. Okay, so רמב"ן Ramban says in these cases,
yes, הקדש hekdesh owns it, but since nobody sanctified it, it does
not have קדושת הגוף. That also... it doesn't have like an intrinsic
status of קדושה. kedusha That also helps us understand the debate of
גידולי הקדש, gidulei hekdesh, fruit that grows from the tree. Right? Again,
the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here, who is the first opinion...
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said that there's no מעילה, Meila רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi said there is. Now here, רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot
are interestingly silent because
how
can you say... can you really say that if הקדש hekdesh owns
a tree and fruit grow from it that הקדש Hekdesh doesn't own
the fruit? Presumably they definitely own the fruit. So what's the debate?
Do they think that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הקדש Hekdesh
doesn't own the fruit that grows from its tree? Maybe so, they
don't say. But for the רמב"ן Ramban it works very nicely. Of
course הקדש Hekdesh owns the fruit, nobody's debating that. The point is
nobody sanctified the fruit. But it's a little different than the well
and the water, because the water is completely distinct from the well,
it's something else, it just fell into the well. The fruit grew
out of the tree that was verbally sanctified. There was a קדושת
הפה. kedushat hapeh. have the tree. So therefore, Rabbi Yehuda is saying,
I don't care if there was a קדושת הפה kedushat hapeh of
the tree. Nobody verbally sanctified the fruit, so the fruit itself is
no מעילה Meila because that has not been directly sanctified. And Rabbi
Yossi says, no, the fruit that was produced by the tree, the
status of the tree extends to the fruit. And therefore, since the
tree was sanctified, the fruit itself has the same sanctity and there
is מעילה Meila by the fruit.
Is it -- is there מעילה Meila. on a בכור? bechor? No.
Thinking
about פדיון בכורות, pidyon bechorot, right.
And also nobody sanctified --
oh, you mean a בכור bechor like a human
בכור?
bechor? No, I was thinking an animal.
Oh, an animal, yes, that's קדושת קרבן, kedushat korban, so there is
מעילה.
Meila But nobody sanctified it.
That -- oh, I see. That is a very good -- that
is a very good point.
That's a good point. Yeah, that's an interesting point according to the
רמב״ן. Ramban. Now, there is a מצוה mitzvah to do קדושת פה
kedushat peh for a בכור bechor of an animal anyway.
I thought you were just making a joke because it was קדושת
-- firstborn humans, even though we give five שקלים, shekalim, if you
don't give five שקלים shekalim there's no איסור הנאה issur hanaah on
the baby בכור. bechor. But anyway, but that
is
a good question.
But even if you don't say that, it's still קדוש. kadosh.
Right, it's קדוש מרחם. kadosh merachem. What would the רמב״ן Ramban say
about a בכור? bechor?
It might be different, something that actually is going למזבח. That might
be enough because, you know, even without the קדושת פה. kedushat peh.
But you're right, it's like the פירות. peirot. It's like the fruit
from the tree.
No, the mother doesn't -- isn't קדוש. kadosh.
Yeah, but it's like a בן פקועה. ben pekuah. The status comes
out of
the -- yeah, but it's still -- the רמב״ן Ramban says that
-- the point is, is the only way to get that status
of intrinsic קדושה kedusha, through קדושת הפה, kedushat hapeh, or is there
some other way? You know, in a case where it's something like
-- but anyway, but it's a good question. In a case where
it's only קדושה, kedusha it's only relevance to the בית המקדש is
the fact that it's fell into הקדש's Hekdesh yard and הקדש Hekdesh
owns it, and there they say there's nothing that gives it this
higher -- this -- this status. It's just owned by the בית
המקדש. Something here where the תורה Torah is automatically assigning it קדושת
קרבן kedushat korban could be different. But it's a good question.
Yeah, so I want to understand. According to those -- you said
there were two models. One was the כוונה, kavanah, the other was
the -- you know, הקדש hekdesh. doesn't have a קנין חצר. kinyan
chatzer. Right. So but even according to the -- הקדש hekdesh, doesn't
have קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer, but we would still say that you
still can't use the rainwater?
I don't know, maybe מפני דרכי שלום mipnei darchei shalom or something.
I don't know, it's not clear. You're right. According to the --
I mean, maybe דרבנן derabbanan or something. I don't know, they don't
spell it out. Okay, so anyway, so that -- so everybody agrees
-- seems to agree there's no מעילה Meila by the rainwater in
the well for the reason we said, either it's not owned by
הקדש Hekdesh, or the רמב״ן's Ramban model, which I like a lot
more, which is that it's owned but it's not קדוש. kadosh. But
the fruit that grows from the tree, there's that debate of does
the קדושה Kedushah. of the tree extend to the fruit. Okay, תניא,
tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, beraisa, אמר רבי, amar Rabbi, said Rabbi, נראין דברי רבי יהודה
בבור ושובך, nirin divrei Rabbi Yehuda bebor veshovach, Rabbi Yehuda seems correct
in the case of the cistern and the pigeon coop that there
is no מעילה Meila by the water and the pigeons, ודברי רבי
יוסי בשדה ואילן, vedivrei Rabbi Yossi besadeh veilan, and Rabbi Yossi by
the field and the tree where there is מעילה Meila by the
fruit that grows from the tree. The גמרא Gemara says, הי מאי,
hai mai, what do you mean? What's he talking about? בשלמא נראין
דברי רבי יהודה בבור ושובך, bishlama nirin divrei Rabbi Yehuda bebor veshovach,
מכלל דפליגי בשדה ואילן, miklal depeleigi besadeh veilan, I get that he
says I agree with Rabbi Yehuda by the cistern and the pigeon
coop because the debate -- Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Yossi are debating
even other cases as well. They're debating the case of, you know,
of the fruit of the tree. So he's saying although Rabbi Yehuda
says there's no מעילה Meila by all of these, I agree with
him just in the case of the cistern and the pigeon coop.
I don't agree with Rabbi Yehuda in the case of the fruit
of the tree. That part of your statement makes sense,
Rabbi. אלא נראין דברי רבי יוסי בשדה ואילן, ela nirin divrei Rabbi
Yossi besadeh veilan, and you say Rabbi Yossi seems to be correct
in the case of the field, so that sounds like Rabbi Yossi
said his הלכה halacha in a wide range of cases, but you
only agreed with him in the case of the field and the
tree. But that's not true! Rabbi Yossi was only arguing about
the case of
the field and the tree explicitly because of גידולי הקדש. gidulei Hekdesh.
So what do you mean, oh I think Rabbi Yossi is right
in this case? Like you think he's right in this case and
you disagree with another. It means you think he's right. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so וכי תימא לדבריו דרבי יהודה קאמר, vechi teima
lidevarav deRabbi Yehuda kaamar,
maybe what Rabbi Yossi is saying is like, look Rabbi Yehuda, I
think you're wrong in all those cases. I think there's מעילה Meila
even in the case of the cistern and the rainwater, but at
least you should agree to me by the tree. But maybe to
read it that Rabbi Yossi himself is saying that there's מעילה me'ilah.
by everything
and Rabbi is פסקנינג paskening like him only in the case of
the tree, you can't. say that. דתניא, De-tanya, it's clear that רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi only disagrees in the case of the tree. אמר
רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, אין אני רואה דברי רבי יהודה בשדה
ואילן. ein ani ro'eh divrei Rabi Yehuda basadeh ve-ilan.
I don't agree with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by the tree and
the field, meaning by the other stuff, the cistern and the rainwater,
I agree, but the field and the tree I don't, מפני שהן
גידולי הקדש. mipnei she-hen gidulei hekdesh. So because they grow from הקדש.
Hekdesh, בשדה ואילן הוא דאינו רואה. Besadeh ve-ilan hu de-eino ro'eh.
He's only disagreeing in the case of the field and the tree.
הא בבור ושובך רואה, ha-be-vor ve-shovach ro'eh, in the cistern and the
pigeon coop, he does agree that there's no מעילה. me'ilah, I know.
So clear. No, but the question is, so why did רבי Rebbe
say, I agree with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in this case? רבי
Rebbe should have just said, I פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. That's what רבי, Rebbe, so that's what we're asking. It's clear
what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is saying, it's not clear why רבי
Rebbe is saying I agree with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in the
case of the tree. What you're really saying is you פסקן pasken
like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, which is what the גמרא Gemara re-reads
it as saying. הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar, here's what he means. נראין
דברי רבי יהודה לרבי יוסי בבור ושובך שאף רבי יוסי לא נחלק
עליו אלא בשדה ואילן.
nirin divrei Rabi Yehuda
le-Rabi Yosi be-vor ve-shovach she-af Rabi Yosi lo nechelak alav ela be-sadeh
ve-ilan. Okay,
what רבי Rebbe is really saying is that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
himself, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position makes sense to רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. When it says when רבי Rebbe is saying I agree with
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he's not saying I agree with רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi disagrees with רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. What he's saying is everybody agrees to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
I agree to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
agrees to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the case of the well
because the whole debate was in the case of the tree. שאף
רבי יוסי לא נחלק עליו אלא בשדה ואילן, she-af Rabi Yosi lo
nechelak alav ela be-sadeh ve-ilan, אבל בבור ושובך מודה ליה, aval be-vor
ve-shovach modei leh, but in the case of the well and the
cistern he agrees, it basically means bottom line it's saying that רבי
Rebbe is saying I פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. Okay,
fine, we can concede the case of the cistern and the water,
that's a case where there's no מעילה, me'ilah. but the case of
the tree I agree with רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, it grows from
הקדש, Hekdesh there is מעילה. me'ilah Alright, so that's very nice, we
have those two categories. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan,
we taught. הקדישן ריקנין ואחר כך נתמלאו. hikdishan rekanin ve-achar kach nitmal'u.
So this is our case, he sanctified these things empty and then
they got filled up. Now are we talking about a tree or
are we talking about a cistern? Not clear yet. Okay.
מועלין בהן ואין מועלין במה שבתוכן. mo'alin bahen ve-ein mo'alin be-mah she-betochan.
There's מעילה me'ilah by them but not by what's in them. What?
The tree? I know, it sounds like a well, but the גמרא
Gemara is going to deal with both possibilities. Okay, ורבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אומר אף מועלין במה שבתוכן, ve-Rabi Elazar be-Rabi Shimon omer af
mo'alin be-mah she-betochan, it even is with what's in them. So it
would seem like this easy thing to do is to read it
to be about the cistern and the water, no, but the problem
with the cistern and the water is that nobody until now has
said that you're מועל mo'el with the water that fills the cistern.
The only place we've seen a debate so far is the case
of the tree. So that's why we're going to push it.
I understand. So let's take a look. Don't blame me, blame the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא מחלוקת בשדה ואילן. Amar Rava machloket be-sadeh ve-ilan.
Okay, so we're talking about a field. I mean a field you
could say I think it's במה שבתוכן, be-mah she-betochan, the field works
better than the tree. תנא קמא סבר לה כרבי יהודה, tana kamma
savar lah ke-Rabi Yehuda, the תנא קמא tana kamma holds like רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that מעילה me'ilah. does not apply to things that
grow on a tree. ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סבר לה כרבי יוסי,
ve-Rabi Elazar be-Rabi Shimon savar lah ke-Rabi Yosi, and רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon holds like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that
when it grows from on a tree or grows in a field
there is מעילה. me'ilah. That at least makes a nice matchup of
the debates. Although the language is strange, I agree with you.
אבל בבור ושובך דברי הכל מועלין בהן ואין מועלין במה שבתוכן. aval
be-vor ve-shovach divrei hakol mo'alin bahen ve-ein mo'alin be-mah she-betochan. Everybody agrees
there's no מעילה. me'ilah So far we've never found anybody to say
there's מעילה me'ilah there, and we want to keep it that way.
Okay, it's a very interesting thing, right? Like the relationship between something
that comes from something else. Right. I mean like even like a
fetus. Right. In other words, it's a very is it independent, is
it right? Conceptually.
Right. Right. And it certainly can have an independent identity, but here
what we want to know is sort of like does the status
transfer? Yeah. Right. Exactly. אמר אביי ואלא הא דתניא הקדישן מלאים
מועלין בהן ובמה שבתוכן. Amar Abaye ve-ela ha de-tanya hikdishan mele'im mo'alin
bahen u-ve-mah she-betochan. If you sanctified them when they were already filled,
you have מעילה me'ilah with them and what's in them. ורבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון מחליף. ve-Rabi Elazar be-Rabi Shimon machalif. And רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon reverses.
Now, it's a funny phrase מחליף, machalif, but the רשב"ם Rashbam says
the reason it says that is because רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi
Eliezer ben Shimon is saying the sort of ironic or paradoxical position.
He is saying if you sanctify the thing and then it fills
up, okay, then there's מעילה me'ilah by what it got filled with.
But if it was already filled when you sanctified it, then there's
no מעילה me'ilah, with what was in it. Which is like bizarre!
The stuff was already in the well or in on the tree
or wherever it was and I sanctified it and there's no מעילה,
me'ilah? but if it came later there is מעילה? Me'ilah, So we're
going to have to figure that out. That like makes no sense.
But as we're going to work to figure it out, we're going
to sort of try to figure out, are we talking about a
well or are we talking about a tree? Okay, so until now
the claim was a tree, which was not the simple language, but
at least it maps onto the previous debate. So let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
ואי בשדה ואילן, Ve-i be-sadeh ve-ilan, you want to say that the
debate here is about the tree, the fruit that grows on the
tree, so אמאי מחליף, amai machalif, what logic would there be to
say... That when stuff grows from a tree it's מעילה, Me'ilah. but
if the apples were on the tree and you sanctified it, there's
no מעילה. Me'ilah That doesn't make any sense. Okay, now it shouldn't
also make sense with water in a well either, but we'll see
where we're going to go. אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava מחלוקת
בבור ושובך. Machlokes be-vor ve-shovach. So the first explanation was the one
that was a nice mapping on an earlier debate, but a hard
read of the language, which was they were debating the case of
the cistern and the water, right? It comes in, it's owned by
הקדש, Hekdesh's I'm going to read this like the הרמב"ן, Ramban, but
it hasn't been, I'm sorry, I misstated that, I jumped ahead. The
first debate was the first way of reading it was the case
of the tree and the fruit. Okay, you sanctified the tree, the
fruit grew, you didn't sanctify the tree, the fruit, but they grew
from, but the fruit, but they grew from the tree, and that
was the debate of רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי Rebbi Yehuda ve-Rebbi Yosi
of is there מעילה Me'ilah by the fruit? Now we're saying they're
going to be debating the well filled with water. Now, that's going
to be interesting because how does, based on the הרמב"ן Ramban's model,
how can anybody say that there's מעילה Me'ilah by the water? Do
they disagree with this principle? Do they say there could be מעילה
Me'ilah. even without an act of being sanctified? So let's see now
that we're going to say they're debating the well and the water,
what that's based on. Okay, אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava מחלוקת
בבור ושובך. Machlokes be-vor ve-shovach. They are, we are debating the case
of the well and the pigeon coop. אבל בשדה ואילן דברי הכל
מועלין בהן ובמה שבתוכן. Aval bi-sadeh ve-ilan divrei ha-kol mo'alin ba-hen u-ve-mah
she-be-tochan. The case of the tree, גידולי הקדש, Gidulei hekdesh, everybody agrees
to רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi. It grew from something you sanctified, it
has the same קדושה.
Kedushah Is this the החלפה? Hachlafah?
No, no, no, we haven't got to the החלפה Hachlafah yet. First
we're understanding the circumstances of their debate. Everybody mentioned here would agree
that גידולי הקדש Gidulei hekdesh have קדושה Kedushah, and there's מעילה. Me'ilah
All what we're debating is the well and the water. Okay, so
now we have to understand what's the position that there's מעילה Me'ilah
by the water. There's, going by the הרמב"ן, Ramban, there's no קדושת
הפה, Kedushat ha-peh, how could there be מעילה Me'ilah. by the water?
So let's take a look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ובבור ושובך ריקנין במאי פליגי ובמלאין במאי פליגי? U-ve-vor ve-shovach reikanin
be-mai peligi u-ve-mle'in be-mai peligi? So what's the debate when you sanctify
them empty and they fill, and what's the debate when they're already
filled and you sanctify them and how can you have a position
that reverses itself in that case? So let's take a look. So
ריקנין פליגי בפלוגתא דרבי מאיר ורבנן. Reikanin peligi bi-plugta de-Rebbi Meir ve-Rabbanan.
By empty and getting filled with water, they debate the debate of
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the רבנן. Rabbanan. What's the debate of
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבנן? Rabbanan? דתנא קמא סבר לה כרבנן
דאמרי אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. De-tanna kamma savar lah
ke-Rabbanan de-amri ein adam makneh davar she-lo ba la-olam. You can't sanctify
something that has not yet come to the world. So the water
does not yet is not yet in the well, you don't own
it yet, you can't sanctify it.
Wait, wait, wait,
it's מקנה, Makneh, it's not מקדיש. Makdish.
We're assuming the same. We're making a lot of assumptions here. That's
correct, yes. ורבי אליעזר, Ve-Rebbi Eliezer, right, but also remember here that
since we are dealing with קדושת בדק הבית and we're talking about
basically קדושת דמים, the בית המקדש here is owning it as just
property to sell and to use the money, then we are it
is much more in the קניין Kinyan model than in the normal
הקדש, Hekdesh than in a different type of a model. But anyway,
but there's a lot of assumptions, yes. אמירה לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט, Amirah
le-gavoha ke-mesirato le-hedyot, that an act of being מקדיש Makdish is like
an act of doing a קניין, Kinyan, but you are correct to
point that out, that we are making an assumption it's the same
principles. So the Rabbis hold you can't sanctify the water that doesn't
yet exist, that you don't yet own. It doesn't just mean it
doesn't exist cause it's up in the clouds, okay, the pigeons exist,
they just haven't come to your pigeon coop, right? So, but you
don't own it yet, you can't be מקדיש Makdish it. So according
to that, that's what the הרמב"ן Ramban says. You didn't מקדיש Makdish
the water, you didn't מקדיש Makdish the pigeon, you were מקדיש Makdish
the cistern and then later it rained and filled and then it
became owned by הקדש Hekdesh because it's on הקדש Hekdesh property, so
that's קדושה, kedusha, that's without קדושת הפה, Kedushat ha-peh, it's just הקדש
Hekdesh's took possession of it, and therefore there's no מעילה. Me'ilah. So
if you say you can't, you didn't sanctify the future water, you
only sanctified the cistern, then the water becomes owned by הקדש hekdesh
when it rains, but it was never sanctified and therefore there's no
מעילה. Me'ilah That's the position of the
רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Eliezer be-Rebbi Shimon who
says that there is מעילה Me'ilah by water, how could there be
מעילה me'ila. by the water in the well, you didn't sanctify it?
No, סבר כרבי מאיר דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, Savar
ke-Rebbi Meir de-amar adam makneh davar she-lo ba la-olam, who says that
you can sanctify something before it exists. One minute, you, so therefore,
even though you don't yet own the water and you don't yet
own the pigeons, what you're saying is when the water and the
pigeons come under my control, I'm going to sanctify them. So implicitly,
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it's implicit, הרמב"ן Ramban says because this fits
better the הרמב"ן Ramban's whole model, that it's explicit, that what you
actually said explicitly is "I am sanctifying this well and any water
that in the end will fall into that well, I am sanctifying
this pigeon coop and any pigeons that will come into the pigeon
coop." So according to the הרמב"ן, Ramban, the second part of your
statement meant nothing, it's very nice, you think you can't sanctify something
you don't own, we completely ignore that, so you didn't sanctify the
water, you didn't sanctify the pigeons, they become owned by הקדש hekdesh,
because they fall into הקדש hekdesh רשות. Reshut. So that's why there's
no... But according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon,
that act of sanctifying, either implicit or explicit, act of sanctifying the
water that in the end would fall and the pigeons that in
the end would come, works because you could be מקנה דבר שלא
בא לעולם makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam and therefore those do have
קדושת פה kedushat peh and that's why there is מעילה. meilah Now
Michael's bothered. Why is Michael bothered?
Well usually when we say אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם adam
makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam or not, that's what the case with
the tree was, that's where the מחלוקת machloket is. Why? Because you
know the tree is going to bear fruit.
So let's take a look at the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay so, אימור דשמעת ליה לרבי מאיר, eimur dishama say l'Rabbi
Meir,
when does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say you could be מקנה דבר
שלא בא לעולם? makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam? כגון פירות דקל דעבידי
דאתי, kigone peiros dekel d'avid d'asi, like
fruit of a tree, like you sanctified, you kept ownership of the
palm tree and you sanctified the fruit, but the fruit are something
that naturally will come. Now, I gotta tell you, the well will
eventually fill with water. So maybe it's a question about the pigeon
coop. It's not such a question about the well. הני בי מיא
דאתי, hani bi m'aya d'asi, who says that water's ever going to
fall in the well or pigeons will ever go into the coop?
So we're going to see in a minute because the answer, I
understand, but the answer makes it sound like the question was actually
a little bit different. And I thought you were going to ask
something different. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, משתכח לה במיא דארבעים דרך חצירו
לבור, mishtachas lah b'mayim arba'im derech chatzeiro labor, ויונים באים דרך שובכו
לשובך. v'yonim b'aim derech shovcho l'shovach. No, no, no, here we know,
I'm going to first read it this one way and then I'm
going to read it a different way. We know that water will
fall into the well. How do we know water will fall into
the well? Because you know if you've got your, you know, you've
got your yard and it's at an angle and here's the well,
so whenever it rains, right, it goes into the well. And now
why do we have to say it's your yard? Well, because if
it was somebody else's yard maybe they would, you know, build a
wall
or maybe they'd build their own well or something. Of course, why
we don't just assume it'll rain straight into the well, I don't
know. Okay, but that's what it says. It's going to go there,
you know it'll come there. And you've got here your pigeon coop
which is already filled with pigeons. Okay, so there's tons of pigeons
nearby and here's the empty pigeon coop that you have, what do
you call it, that you were מקדיש, makdish, so you know that
they're going to come here. Of course, if you already owned these
pigeons then they're not going to be קדוש kadosh because they're yours.
So what does it mean that they're באים דרך שובכו? ba'im derech
shovcho? Why does it have to be your pigeon coop? So maybe
it means well you already know that this is like a popular
one that pigeons come so that they're going to continue on over
there. But then even if it, but then even if it wasn't
yours, so ר"ש Rash says well if it wasn't yours, you know,
you could build a wall here or something and stop them from
coming. Now all of that is very weird. Like that's what you
need to say to explain that that's how we know pigeons are
going to get into your coop and water's going to get into
your well? When it rains water enters your well and there seems
to be something else going on here because it says the word
שובכו shovcho
and it says חצירו, chatzeiro, it sounds like it's relevant that you
own it. So comes along תוספות Tosafot and רמב"ן Ramban and they
say, and this I thought Michael was the question you were going
to ask, they say one minute here, this is answering a different
question. This is not answering the question of how likely it is
that the water's going to fill, the well's going to fill up
with water. This is answering the question of how, when we say
I could be מקדיש makdish something שלא בא לעולם, she'lo ba l'olam,
that's because when it's בא לעולם ba l'olam I own it. So
if I own my palm tree and I מקדיש makdish the fruit,
that's because if I weren't מקדיש makdish the fruit, who would own
the fruit? Me! Okay, if I say I'm going to buy a
car from Michael and I מקדיש makdish the car that I'm going
to buy from Michael, and if it were to work, it's because
had I not been מקדיש makdish it, it would have been mine.
It would have been, so therefore I have the ability, if you
say you can do this, you have the ability to do it
in the future because in that future time it's yours and you
have rights to it. Okay, that's right, obviously I can't be מקדיש
makdish something that I'm never going to own. Okay, let's say I
say the following: I am hereby מקדיש makdish any, any lost object
after יאוש ye'ush that exists in New York City because it's going
to be הפקר hefker and I'm מקדיש makdish it. Like who the
heck am I to be מקדיש makdish it? You have to own
it first of all in order to be מקדיש makdish it. So
the question here is: how can you be מקדיש makdish the water
that's going to fall into that well? First I מקדיש makdish the
well and then it rains. Well when it's raining, it's no longer
my well, it's הקדש's hekdesh, well. So how can I be מקדיש,
makdish, even if I can be מקדיש makdish something in the future,
that's only if you remove the הקדש, hekdesh. it would have been
mine. But now that the well belongs to הקדש hekdesh and the
שובך shovach belongs to הקדש, hekdesh how could I be מקדיש makdish
the pigeons that are going to fly in later and the water
that's going to fall in later?
The language of the, the model of קניין kinyan and the model
of הקדש. hekdesh Right.
So the answer is, the answer is, באים דרך חצירו, ba'im derech
chatzeiro, באים דרך שובכו, ba'im derech shovcho,
that the reason I can be מקדיש makdish it is because I
do own the water. The ownership, the water that's going to fall
into my yard and is going to be my water and then
go into the well. Because since they're nesting in my property I
take ownership, and then they continue on into this שובך *shovach*, I
am מקדיש makdish *makdish* those pigeons. Why does the רשב"א *Rashba* make
an analogy to קידושי אשה על מנת *Kiddushei Isha Al Menat*? I'm
going to talk about that in a minute. Okay, so it doesn't
fit? I will talk about that in a minute. Okay, so the
point is like this. According to the רמב"ם *Rambam*, we all agree
that there can only be מעילה meilah *me'ilah* on something I'm verbally
מקדיש makdish *makdish*. So what is the debate about the water in
the well? I wasn't verbally מקדיש makdish *makdish* it, it fell into
the well, הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* took possession of it, there's no verbal
הקדשה hakdasha *hakdasha* so therefore there can't be מעילה meilah *me'ilah*. So
רבי אלעזר בן שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon* says no, actually I
hold like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, and I hold that you were
verbally מקדיש makdish *makdish*, either implicit or as the רמב"ם *Rambam* says
explicitly you said, 'I מקדיש makdish *makdish* the well and all future
water. I מקדיש makdish *makdish* the שובך *shovach* and all future pigeons.'
So you were verbally מקדיש makdish *makdish*. How did it work, you
didn't own it yet? You work because you could do it שלא
בא לעולם *shelo ba l'olam*, even though you don't own it. Whatever,
let's practice that. Eventually pigeons go into a coop, water go into
a...
it's at least as much as whatever as fruit comes on a
tree. That's not the issue.
The issue is
you were מקדיש makdish *makdish* it and you have the power to
מקדיש makdish *makdish* something you don't own now that you will in
the future. Ah, you won't own it in the future? You have
to at least own it in the future for that to work.
You will own it in the future. I'm talking about water that's
coming through your yard, I'm talking about pigeons that's coming through your
pigeon coops. So water that you will own and pigeons that you
will own, those you have future מקדיש makdish *makdish* and therefore there's
מעילה meilah. *me'ilah*. So that's how it works according to רבי אלעזר
בן שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon*. Now, what's this long תוספות *Tosafot*
and this long רשב"א *Rashba*? What this long תוספות *Tosafot* and this
long רשב"א *Rashba* are about is that they are very what I
would call academic in the sense that they both of them, starting
with the רשב"א *Rashba*, point out that רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* never
spoke about a palm tree and a fruit that you were מקדיש
*makdish* the fruit שלא בא לעולם *shelo ba l'olam*, and the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says when does רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* say it, by
a דיקלא *dekel* and the fruit and they'll come etc. Says רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* actually said this הלכה *halacha* by a case about
a man that says to a woman, 'I'll be מקדיש *makdish*... I
am... not מקדיש *makdish*, I am מקדש *mekadesh* you על מנת *al
menat* that once I convert, once you convert, if you're a slave,
once your master frees you, once your husband dies' or whatever, all
these cases. Okay, so they have two problems. First of all, how
do we get from there to talk about a palm tree? And
second of all, that's not like עבידא דאתי *avida d'asu*. Why can
we assume that the master's going to free the slave? So basically
what they both point out is that
really the גמרא *Gemara* when it talks... is really not talking about
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. The גמרא *Gemara*'s really talking, I think, it's
like a רב הונא *Rav Huna* who talks about the palm tree
and the גמרא *Gemara* just makes an assumption, it sort of like
lines up these different positions of מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם *makneh
davar shelo ba l'olam*. So רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* starts about this
case of marriage and then it connects to another case of שלא
בא לעולם *shelo ba l'olam*, another case and another case and eventually
we get to the palm tree with the fruit. And then whenever
we talk about רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, we talk about him about
the palm tree and the fruit. But it sort of ignores the
fact that not only was רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* not talking about
that case, but that actually it operates with different parameters, that רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s case actually is not a case where it's likely
to happen. So you can take a look, they try to make
it so that it's not such a big divergence, but that's what
the whole discussion is about. Yes?
Can I just ask a tiny... when you kept referring to שיטות
*shittot* of the רמב"ן *Ramban*? רמב"ן *Ramban* on קידושין *Kiddushin* or בבא
בתרא *Bava Batra*? Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Okay, so
now we got that. That's a great debate. Okay, it's that you
require קדושת פה kedushat peh, *kiddusha sheh peh* and the question is
can it work for the future? Is it like מקנה דבר שלא
בא לעולם *makneh davar shelo ba l'olam*? And if it can work
for the future, it's only if you take possession of it before
it actually then becomes קדוש kadosh *kadosh*. That's answer number one. Now
how about the reverse case? במילא במאי פליגי *bemilai bemai
peligi*?
Now what do they debate when it's filled with water?
Why should there not be קדושה *kiddusha* if the thing is filled
with water already? Or I mean מעילה meilah *me'ilah*? So אמר רבא
amar Rava כגון שהקדיש בור bor סתם *Amar Rava kegon shehikdish bor
stam*, because as opposed to the previous case, I'm going to read
this like the רמב"ן *Ramban*, the previous case you said 'I am
מקדיש *makdish* בור bor. ומימיו *bor u'meimav*.' So the בור bor. ומימיו
*bor u'meimav* became a קדושת פה kedushat peh, *kiddusha sheh peh* for
the future. But here it was already filled with water and you
just say 'I am מקדיש *makdish* the בור *bor*.' Okay, so רבי
אלעזר בן שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon* סבר לה כאבוה *savar lah
k'avuah*, he holds like his father דאמר דנים דין גבוה מדין הדיוט
hedyot, *d'amar danim din gavoah midin hedyot*. Okay, so the father says
that you look at הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* like you look at a
lay case, meaning for the purpose of... this is you might remember
before his father רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* said that if you're מקדיש
*makdish* a field you also give the חרוב *charub* and the sycamore
and all these things, right? Remember, so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
*Tanna Kamma* said oh well once it's הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* or a
gift you give a lot of stuff in the field you normally
otherwise wouldn't give. People remember that from
before vaguely? and other things are not included in a field in
a sale, they're not included in הקדש. hekdesh So רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rebbi Eleazar bar Rebbi Shimon holds like his father, that we
don't assume more is included in הקדש hekdesh than is included in
a sale. So in a sale, what happens when I sell a
well? Do I sell the water? Now we're finally tying it back
to our משנה. mishnah. Okay, so it says like this, רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rebbi Eleazar bar Rebbi Shimon סבר כאבוה savar k'avuh דאמר
דנין דין גבוה מדין הדיוט. d'amar danin din gavoha mi'din hedyot. Number
one, what's included in an act of הקדש is the same as
what's included when you sell it. Okay, מה דין הדיוט מה דאמר
בירה זבינה לך מיא לא זבינה לך. ma din hedyot ma d'amar
bira zvina lach maya lo zvina lach. By the case of selling
it to a layperson, if you have a cistern filled with water,
you can say I just sold the cistern, not the water. אף
דין גבוה בירה הקדיש מיא לא הקדיש. af din gavoha bira hikdish
maya lo hikdish. You only sold the cistern, not the water. So
if you say I am מקדיש the well with the water, then
the water is קדוש kadosh, and there's מעילה meilah if there's current
water or even if there's future water, because מקדיש דבר שלא בא
לעולם. makdish davar she'lo ba l'olam. But if you just said I
am selling the well, okay, I'm מקדיש the well, then it's only
the well and not the water and there's no מעילה by the
water. So the גמרא says one minute, ובדין הדיוט לא? u'v'din hedyot
lo? Are you telling me that in a case of laypeople that
you don't sell the water? והתנן v'hatnan our משנה mishnah teaches מכר
בור מכר מימיו machar bor machar memav that actually when you sell
the cistern you do sell the water. So even if הקדש is
no greater than הדיוט, hedyot but even in a הדיוט hedyot. the
word well includes the water. So אמר רבא מתניתין יחידאה היא. matnitin
yichida-ah hi. No, our משנה mishnah is not a unanimous opinion, it's
a single opinion. דתניא d'tanya we taught in a ברייתא braita מכר
בור לא מכר מימיו machar bor lo machar memav that actually you
didn't sell the water with the well. רבי נתן אומר Rebbi Natan
omer מכר בור מכר מימיו machar bor machar memav you did sell
the water. So one more time, let us talk about, let us
say, let us again review how the debates make sense. You were
מקדיש a cistern with the water, you said explicitly, I מקדיש בור
ומימיו, makdish bor u'memav, but there is no water in it. So
in that case, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says the בור is
מעילה but not the water because אין אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא
לעולם. ein adam makdish davar she'lo ba l'olam. And רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rebbi Eleazar bar Rebbi Shimon says the water when it rains
will be קדוש, kadosh אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם. adam makdish
davar she'lo ba l'olam. אה, Ah, and in a case where it's
coming through your field, so you'll take possession of it before it
becomes קדוש kadosh, and therefore you'll be in a position to be
sanctifying it. That's one debate. And in both cases though, you do
have קדושת פה, that's why there's מעילה. Case number two is you're
saying I am מקדיש the בור. You didn't say מימיו. memav. I'm
מקדיש the בור. There's water in the well. Okay, so תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says look, first of all, if you sell a well
you sell the water, so if you're מקדיש a well you're מקדיש
the water. So you were מקדיש the water. Number two, even if
when you sell a well you didn't sell water, by הקדש we
assume you give more than you give in a sale. So the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma. says I'm going to assume the water was
part of your הקדשה even though you only mentioned the well. That's
the תנא קמא. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Eleazar bar Rebbi Shimon
says I disagree on both points. Number one, I assume that הקדש
is no different than a הדיוט. hedyot And number two, I assume
that when you sell a well you don't sell the water, against
our
משנה, mishnah, even in a הדיוט case if you sell a well
you don't sell water, and a הקדש is no different. And therefore
when you're מקדיש the well, you were not מקדיש the water, so
that's why רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Eleazar bar Rebbi Shimon ironically
could be the reverse. But it's not really the reverse because in
the first case you explicitly said the water, so there's מעילה by
the water. The second case you only said the well, and therefore
the water wasn't included, and therefore he says that the water does
not come together with the well and there's no מעילה by the
water. So that was a lot of fun, I thought. I don't
know how if you guys followed or were lost. But I do
think that the interesting thing here is this רמב"ן'ס Ramban's idea, this
is really the thing to walk away with, which is that הקדש
can own something without the thing being קדוש, kadosh right? And that
it can be in the ownership of הקדש or maybe it's קדוש
but it's not בת קדושת מעילה bat kedushat meilah without it being,
that requires קדושת פה, and there actually is a difference between the
question of ownership and the question of the קדושה, the status of
the object itself. Okay, I hope everybody has a wonderful יום טוב
and גוט סדרים gut sedarim and the time in the.